Visual materials from the Booker T. Washington papers
Prints & Photographs Division, Library of Congress
Visual materials from the Booker T. Washington papers 1889-1935 bulk 1897-1915
LOT 13164
701 items (chiefly photographic prints); 57 x 41 cm. or smaller.
Prints & Photographs Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Photographs document the activities of Booker T. Washington as a leader and agrarian organizer in the South at the turn of the century. Many depict Booker T. Washington’s speaking engagements at such places as Ocala, Tallahasee, and Daytona, Fla.; Mound Bayou, Miss.; and Baton Rouge, La. The collection also includes photographs that document classes and activities at the Tuskegee Normal and Industrial Institute, Tuskegee, Ala., including a parade for the celebration of the visit of President Theodore Roosevelt on October 24, 1905; celebrations for the twenty-fifth anniversary of the Institute in 1906; and students building dormitories and other facilities. Also includes a group portrait of the faculty of the Institute in 1897, as well as a few images of such faculty members as Frederick Douglass, Emmett Scott, and George Washington Carver. In addition, the collection contains portraits of other African Americans, including Blanche K. Bruce, Henry O. Tanner, John R. Lynch, Richard T. Greener, and John M. Langston, as well as alumni of Tuskegee Institute. Also includes portraits of African American students at other schools in the South. Many images are unique because of personal inscriptions to Booker T. Washington.
For information about Prints and Photographs Division collections and services, see the Prints & Photographs Division's Reading Room Home Page.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Bedou, A. P. (Arthur P.), 1882-1966, photographer.; Johnston, Frances Benjamin, 1864-1952, photographer.; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915, collector.; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915.
Organizations
Tuskegee Normal and Industrial Institute--1880-1940.
Subjects
African Americans--1880-1940.; Buildings--1880-1940.; Educational facilities--United States--1880-1940.; Floats (Parades)--Alabama--Tuskegee--1900-1910.; Public speaking--1900-1920.; School children--1880-1940.; Schools--United States--1890-1940.; Students--1890-1940.; Universities & colleges--United States--1890-1940.; Women--Education--United States--1880-1940.; Women--Education--United States--1880-1940.
Form/Genre
Albumen prints--1880-1920.; Gelatin silver prints--1890-1940.; Group portraits--1880-1940.; Photomechanical prints--1890-1940.; Portraits--1880-1940.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Transfer; Manuscript Division (Booker T. Washington papers); 1973 (DLC/PP-1973:148), 1995 (DLC/PP-1995:013).
Additional form available
Digitized images of some items in the collection and their associated identifying information are available through the Prints & Photographs Online Catalog, by searching using the call number, "LOT 13164."
Surrogates
Six original film negatives are stored offsite under the filing series designation LC-W2723-1 through LC-W2723-6. One glass lantern slide is stored under the filing designation LC-W2733-1. Surrogates for these images in the form of color laser photocopies have been interfiled within the LOT.
The LOT also includes original damaged photoprints which have been reformatted as digital surrogates for access purposes. These digitized images were printed and have been interfiled within the LOT for reference purposes. The original damaged photographs cannot be served.
Biographical Note
Booker T. Washington was born into slavery in 1856 and after Emancipation grew up in the Kanawha Valley of West Va. At the age of 16 he enrolled in the Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute, Va. In 1881, on the recommendation of staff of the Hampton Institute, he was hired to found a school for African Americans in Tuskegee, Ala. Booker T. Washington became a prominent leader as the result of his fund-raising efforts for Tuskegee. By 1895, Washington had a reputation as a public speaker which is reflected in this collection. He gained the respect of Theodore Roosevelt, who became a trustee of Tuskegee Normal and Industrial Institute in 1910. Washington died at Tuskegee on November 14, 1915 shortly after a speaking engagement in the Northeast.
Scope and Content Note
Photographs document the activities of Booker T. Washington as a leader and agrarian organizer in the South at the turn of the century. Many depict Booker T. Washington's speaking engagements at such places as Ocala, Tallahasee, and Daytona, Fla.; Mound Bayou, Miss.; and Baton Rouge, La. The collection also includes photographs that document classes and activities at the Tuskegee Normal and Industrial Institute, Tuskegee, Ala., including a parade for the celebration of the visit of President Theodore Roosevelt on October 24, 1905; celebrations for the twenty-fifth anniversary of the Institute in 1906; and students building dormitories and other facilities. Also includes a group portrait of the faculty of the Institute in 1897, as well as a few images of such faculty members as Frederick Douglass, Emmett Scott, and George Washington Carver. In addition, the collection contains portraits of other African Americans, including Blanche K. Bruce, Henry O. Tanner, John R. Lynch, Richard T. Greener, and John M. Langston, as well as alumni of Tuskegee Institute. Also includes portraits of African American students at other schools in the South. Many images are unique because of personal inscriptions to Booker T. Washington.
Organization of the Papers
Arranged by subject and size into twelve sub-groups as follows: Booker T. Washington portraits and memorials (LOT 13164-A); Washington at public speaking engagements (LOT 13164-B); Tuskegee Normal and Industrial Institute (LOT 13164-C); Portraits (LOT 13164-D and LOT 13164-E); Colleges & Universities (LOT 13164-F); Canning & Poultry Club Conference, Caroline Co., Va., Aug. 8, 1913 (LOT 13164-G); YMCA buildings and facilities (LOT 13164-H); Identified and unidentified buildings (LOT 13164-I and LOT 13164-J); Agricultural workers (LOT 13164-K); Miscellaneous (LOT 13164-L).
http://lccn.loc.gov/99472031
Overview of Collection Arrangement and Content
- Portraits, statues, and memorials of Booker T. Washington and his family ca. 1890-1935, LOT 13164-A (Box 1 (F size) and Box 6 (H size))
  Also includes group portraits of Washington family members; a reproduction of a landscape painting by Mrs. Frank R. Hill entitled "Mt. Booker Washington," (1904); a design for a memorial portrait group designed and copyrighted by photographer C.M. Battey (c1911); one portrait of Margaret Murray Washington.
- Washington at public speaking engagements ca. 1900-1914, LOT 13164-B (Box 1 (F size) and Box 6 (H size))
  Includes Washington addressing large crowds at locations in Arkansas, California, Florida, Louisiana, Mississippi, South Carolina, Tennessee, and Virginia as well as other unidentified locations. Also views of crowds gathered at the various venues; Washington traveling by coach, automobile, and train to locations; some group portraits, including one of Washington posing with Mary McCloud Bethune.
  Arranged alphabetically by city.
- Tuskegee Institute 1890-1910, LOT 13164-C (Box 2 (F size), Box 6 (H size), and Box 8 (OH size))
  Includes campus views of buildings and monuments, student portraits, campus events, including a celebration and parade for President Theodore Roosevelt in 1905 and a 25th anniversary ceremony. Also includes portraits of faculty and alumni; students attending classes.
- Portraits of Washington's associates ca. 1889-1914, LOT 13164-D; All are F size unless otherwise noted. Includes single and group portraits. (Box 3 (F size) and Box 6 (H size))
  Arranged alphabetically by sitter's surname.
  - Altiers, Genoiro 1906 Puerto Rico
  - Amos, Moses, Dr. 1904 Gate City, Georgia
  - Arkansas Business Mens League
  - Baldwin, William, (H size)
  - Borchers, [Edw.?] 1903
  - Bromet, M.S. 1904 Paris
  - Brooks, A. L., Major
  - Brown, E. S. Cambridge, Massachusetts
  - Bruce, Blanche K., (H Size)
  - Campbell, C. Durham
  - Chase, Henry W. Washington, D.C.
  - Coleman, Henry F. Mt. Vernon, Iowa
  - Cooley, Elizabeth Cooley, Elizabeth
  - Cooley, Elizabeth San Antonio, Texas
  - Dowling, Oscar, Dr.
  - Drouillard, Geo. Cliff. Georges Creek
  - Douglass, Frederick
  - Ellison, Geo. S.
  - Evans, [Z?] T. The Corning Mattress Works
  - Fisher, Isaac Branch Normal College
  - Floyd, W. D. Hawkinsville, Alabama
  - Forrester, Stephenie
  - Freeman, Julius Wilson, North Carolina
  - Gibbs, M. W. [Washington, D.C.]
  - Greener, Richard T., (H size)
  - Griggs, E. M. [Texas]
  - Guy, Ira O. [Kansas]
  - Haas, Henry Hubert, L.L.D. 1906 Roanoke, Virginia
  - Hardin, Mrs. G. C., and little Margarette
  - Harford, Mark A.
  - Herren, John W. Atlanta, Georgia
  - Jackson, and Emmett J. Scott
  - James, Jim 1911 West Point City
  - Johnson, James W., (photos filed under Moton, Robert R.)
  - Jones, Acie 1911 Thomasville, Georgia
  - Jones, Lula H. 1914
  - Langston, John Mercer, (H size)
  - LeBeouf, Miss
  - Lucas, Dora [Ohio]
  - Lynch, John R., (H size)
  - Lyon, Ernest (Consul-General to the Republic of Liberia), and Emmett J. Scott 1909
  - Marr, J. M. Moundbayou, Mississippi
  - Martin, Isaac D. [Alabama], (2 poses)
  - Mason, [W. G.]
  - Maxwell, Minnie P. Zenia, Ohio
  - Maytes, A. L. Chicago, Illinois
  - Millers Wonderful Musical Family of Washington, D.C.
  - Millie & Christine (Siamese twins)
  - Mitchell 1906 [Illinois]
  - Monteria Silva, F. R. 1907 Rio de Janeiro, Brazil
  - Morris, S. L.
  - Moton, Robert R. and James W. Johnson [after 1915]
  - Payton, J. W. [South Carolina]
  - Plummer, D. J. Bournemouth, England
  - Powell, Annie M. Washington, D.C.
  - Pratt, Lawton L. [1913]
  - Reid, William Cooper 1903 Fulton, Mississippi
  - Roosevelt family
  - Roosevelt, Theodore 1908
  - Sanghorne, Edw. T. [1910]
  - Scott, Emmett J., (2 poses)
  - Sheridan, James Jay 1903 Chicago
  - Simons, H. L Columbia, South Carolina
  - Soga, A. Kirkland East London, South Africa
  - Swann, J. Richard
  - Tanner, Henry O., (H size)
  - Terborg, William Surinam
  - Terry, Matt
  - [Toicard, C.?] 1905 Haiti, (2 poses)
  - Walker, S. C. [California]
  - Watkins, son of Lee W.
- Unidentified portraits ca. 1890-ca. 1915, LOT 13164-E (Box 4 (F size) and Box 7 (H size))
  Includes men, women, and children. Also group portraits.
- Colleges and schools (excluding Tuskegee) ca. 1900-1916, LOT 13164-F (Boxes 5 (F size) and Box 7 (H size))
  Includes public schools and colleges primarily in the South; school buildings and group portraits of students standing in front of school buildings; campus views; students attending classes. Also two portraits of Hawaiian school children; one portrait of Japanese school children.
  Arranged alphabetically by school name.
- Canning & Poultry Club Conference, Caroline Co. Aug. 8, 1913, LOT 13164-G (Box 5 (F size))
- YMCA 1912-ca. 1915, LOT 13164-H (Box 5 (F size))
  Includes buildings and activities at YMCA facilities in Arundel-on-the-Bay, Md., Bexton, Iowa, Chicago, Ill., Columbus, Ga., Indianapolis, Ind., Philadelphia, Washington, D.C.
- Buildings ca. 1900-ca. 1915, LOT 13164-I (Box 5 (F size))
  Residences, commercial buildings, and churches. Includes the Frederick Douglass home in Anacostia, Washington, D.C. Includes views in Alabama, Florida, Kansas, Maryland, Massachusetts, Mississippi, Tennessee, and Virginia.
- Unidentified buildings ca. 1900-ca. 1915, LOT 13164-J (Box 5 (F size))
  Exterior views of dwellings and commercial buildings.
- Agricultural workers ca. 1905-ca. 1915, LOT 13164-K (Box 5 (F size))
  Children and adults working or posing in gardens. One group portrait of two aged women posing in front of a tent.
- Miscellaneous subjects ca. 1900-ca. 1910, LOT 13164-L (Box 5 (F size))
  Includes city views, some buildings, people at unidentified events, other unidentified subjects. One unidentified color waterfront view; one praline candy box with a portrait of two women.
Index to Photographers in LOT 13164
Names of photographers and studios--and the cities and states in which they operated-- are noted below as they appear on the photographs. Studio names appear in direct order; personal names in invented order (i.e., filed by surname).
Abercromby, H.A., Orlando, FL LOT 13164-E
Audiotrium Studio, Atlanta, GA LOT 13164-D
Battey, C.M., Tuskegee Inst. LOT 13164-F; LOT 13164-K
Bedou, A.P., New Orleans, LA LOT 13164-A; LOT 13164-B; LOT 13164-C; LOT 13164-E; LOT 13164-F; LOT 13164-I; LOT 13164-L
Bell, J.S., Portland, OR LOT 13164-A
Bell's, C.M., Washington, DC LOT 13164-D
Bilbrey, Tuskegee, AL LOT 13164-E
Bilbrey, G.M., Tuskegee, AL LOT 13164-E
Brown & Co., Detroit, MI LOT 13164-A
Burt, G. W., Moundbayou, Miss. LOT 13164-F; LOT 13164-I
Campbell Studio, Honea Path, SC LOT 13164-D
Chapman, J.R., West Indies LOT 13164-D
Cleary, J.W., [Jamaica] LOT 13164-L
Colman, Montgomery, AL LOT 13164-E
Connel-Irwin, Martins Ferry, OH LOT 13164-D
Cooke, E. W., Snow Hill, AL LOT 13164-K
Cox Brothers, Tuskegee, AL LOT 13164-E
Cumming, Geo. W., Greensboro, AL LOT 13164-E
Cuneo Photo Studio, Euterpe & Dryades LOT 13164-D
Detroit Publishing Company LOT 13164-C
Dolan's Studio, Way Cross, GA LOT 13164-E
Folsom, A.H., Roxbury, MA LOT 13164-J
Forest, O.V. LOT 13164-E
Gandy, John M. LOT 13164-B
Gray, Boston, MA LOT 13164-D
Gretter, Frankport LOT 13164-E
Groeninger Photo, Baltimore, MD LOT 13164-L
Harding, Franklin, LA LOT 13164-E
Jacotin, Charles, Paris, France LOT 13164-E
Jackson, E.W. LOT 13164-D; LOT 13164-F
Johnston, Frances Benjamin LOT 13164-C
Jones, Baltimore, MD LOT 13164-E
Kaufmann's, Pittsburgh, PA LOT 13164-E
Kerfoot, C.E., Washington, DC LOT 13164-D
Killick, J. H., London, England LOT 13164-E
Ladde, M.H., Amsterdam "LOT 13164-D
Lingwood & Jakins, East London, South Africa LOT 13164-D
Livingston, Chas. S., Montgomery, AL LOT 13164-E
McMullan, C.H., Greenville, AL LOT 13164-F
Macon Art Gallery, Macon, GA LOT 13164-E
Marshall-Jackson Company, Chicago, IL LOT 13164-A
Maury, Salem [VA] LOT 13164-D
Mitchell, J.E., Studio, Washington, DC LOT 13164-E
Moore, R.N., [Baltimore, MD] LOT 13164-L
Morse, Chicago, IL LOT 13164-E
Pach Bros., NY LOT 13164-D
Partridge, Geo. H., Chicago, IL LOT 13164-E
Peck, Palo Alto, CA LOT 13164-D
Polk, P.H., Tuskegee Institute, AL LOT 13164-E
Rapid Art Photography, Bournemouth, England LOT 13164-D
Robinson, Chas. D., Tuskegee, AL LOT 13164-A; LOT 13164-D
Roller Printing and Paper Co., Canton, OH LOT 13164-L
Scurlock, Washington, D.C. LOT 13164-D; LOT 13164-H; LOT 13164-K
Shepherd, St. Paul, MN LOT 13164-A
Shepherd, 27 E. 7th St., St. Paul, MN LOT 13164-A
Service Engraving Co., Montgomery, AL LOT 13164-E
Shumacher, Los Angeles, CA LOT 13164-A
Siegel Studio, The, Chicago, Ill. LOT 13164-E
Taylor, Nashville, TN LOT 13164-E
Teddinghaus, E.B., Birmingham, AL LOT 13164-D
Thomas, E.L., Anderson, SC LOT13164-A
Tressler, Montgomery, AL LOT 13164-E
Turner, A., Washington, DC LOT 13164-A
Tuskegee Institute LOT 13164-C
Utica Eng. Co., Utica, NY LOT 13164-I
Watkins, Palestine, TX LOT 13164-D
We-He, Topeka, Kansas LOT 13164-D
Wendt, Boonton, NJ LOT 13164-D
Winsor, Evanston, [IL] LOT 13164-D